Hello! In this episode of Bug
Bounty Reports Explained, I have a
$29,000 arbitrary file read vulnerability
in GitLab. The bug had to do with symlinks
and I'm quite surprised we don't see
this trick used more often. Anyway,
the report was submitted by William Bowling whose
reports I regularly cover on my channel because
they are really, really good. So is this one
so without further ado, enjoy my explanation!
On GitLab, we can create groups and milestones
within them which isn't that important but
important is the fact that we can also upload
files as attachments to these descriptions.
And GitLab can work as gitlab.com, the global
instance, but it can also work as self-hosted
one which you install in, for example, your
own company. And if you create a group in one
instance and then you want to move everything
into another one, GitLab allows you to do
this by simply importing the URL of the GitLab
instance and also the access token. GitLab can
then go and fetch all the information about your
original group and import it to another instance.
For this particular report, the setup that
William created looks like this: from gitlab.com,
you import a group which actually imports itself
also from gitlab.com. The reason is that we don't
care about importing most of the things. There is
only one file that we will have to change and our
proxy server changes one single response and the
rest of requests go simply back to gitlab.com but
gitlab.com does not know about it. Let's talk
about symlinks. Symlinks or symbolic links are
files that refer to other files on the filesystem.
There are two types of them and we are talking
about soft links which don't actually store the
file's data but they refer to the actual file's
location. You can think of it as a shortcut. And
this is the command that I would use to create a
symbolic link to my /etc/passwd file and the
symbolic link itself is called 'symlink'.
If I do anything on this file, the system will
work as if I was working on /etc/passwd file.
The attack scenario we could try is to upload
a file - a symlink to the server, referring the
/etc/passwd on the server, hoping that the
server will resolve the symlink and give us the
/etc/passwd file or any other file from the
server. But the problem of this approach is that
the browser, when we do this, will just upload
our own /etc/passwd file to the server. In fact,
when I first learned about this vulnerability,
that's exactly what I've done - I uploaded my
own file to the server and I thought, for
a second, that I found arbitrary file read.
The problem of this approach is that the
information about the fact that it's
a symlink and not the file is not in its
contents but in information about the file.
And whenever you have a file upload functionality,
you usually only upload file contents and not, for
example, permissions or information that it's a
symlink. Normally this attack won't work. Unless,
you have a functionality that doesn't work on a
single file but works on archives like Zip or tar.
In this case, when importing all the data about
the group from one GitLab instance to another,
our attachments were packed into a tar
archive and then unpacked on the new server.
What GitLab should do to be secure is
it should remove the symlinks on every
single unpacked file. But in this case, it didn't.
This is how you could exploit this on gitlab.com.
First, you create a new group and a new milestone.
In its description, you upload an arbitrary file
- doesn't really matter what are the contents.
It's uploaded to a folder with a random name
which you have to copy. And then locally,
you create the directory with the same name and
inside, you use this command to create a symlink.
The first argument is the file that
you want to steal from the server
and it can be an arbitrary name. Then,
you create an archive with this file.
Now, you create a proxy server that will forward
all requests back to gitlab.com so it can fetch
all the data about the group that you are trying
to import. You only modify a single response - the
one with the uploads.tar.gz file and instead
of requesting this one from an actual GitLab
instance, you return the tar file that you just
created. The vulnerable GitLab instance will then
unpack this file without removing symlinks and all
of a sudden, if you try to open the uploaded file,
you will see the /etc/passwd file
or whatever else you tried to steal.
After some arguments about the risk and, in
particular, about the integrity impact of this
bug, it was classified as critical and the payout
was $29,000. The bug was fixed in GitLab 14.6.2.
If you want to see other reports by William,
check out this GitLab playlist. There is his
$20K RCE in image metadata but also his XSS
that he escalated into an arbitrary file
read. XSS into arbitrary fire read.
A fantastic report! The playlist is
on your screen right now. For now,
thank you for watching and goodbye!